Inventory of the Powell Family Papers 1775-1927
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Papers of the Powell Family, 1785-1927, n.d. (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Papers, 1860-1869. (Box 2-3)
    - Papers, 1865., 65 items. (Box-folder 4:5-7)
      - G[etty] M[cGuire],[Winchester, Virginia], to [Rebecca Powell], n.p., [November 1865?]., 5 pages. ALS. Incomplete, first part of letter missing. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Says Hunter has a small (medical) practice; gives news about what her other brothers[?] are doing; says Willie is doing well despite the time he spent in prison; tells how he was marched by their home last winter by the Yankees and taken to prison; tells how their house was used as a hospital, her family was put under arrest, and they were forced to live with the Yankees for six months; expresses her hatred of the Yankees; discusses how the last four years have changed her; tells how Gert [?] was working in the hospitals and on the battle field, caught a disease and has been bedridden for the last thirteen months; says she was very weak last winter because of the hard work and anxiety; says she could no longer work in the hospitals because of how the sights of war affected her.
      - Douglas F. Forrest, Richmond, [Virginia], to "cousin" [Nina Powell?], [Alexandria, Virginia], 4 December 1865., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Much family news; comments on the meeting of Congress and its result on the restoration of southern property.
      - "Pale Blossom" [Lettie?], Danville, Virginia, to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 12 December 1865., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Writes about Presbyterian Conference she is attending; gives town and family news.
      - "daughter" H[attie] L. P[owell], n.p. to [Selina Powell], [Charlotte County, Virginia?], n.d. [1861-1865?]., Page three of three-page letter. ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Gives history of a family, telling which troop each son is in; comments on the scarcity of paper, which is why she is writing on the back of a letter written to her by her mother.
        Including on back: S[elina Powell], Charlotte C[ourt] H[ouse],[Virginia], to "daughter" [Hattie Powell], n.p. Asks her about her fever and if it is interfering with her teaching; says Mr. Powell visited her for a week; says she will stay in Charlotte all winter; mentions death of Carry Hobson. 1 page. ALS.
      - [Selina Powell], n.p., to "darling" Selina Powell [daughter Nina], General Lee's, Richmond, [Virginia], n.d. [1861-1865]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Sends her a pair of slippers which she made the best she could with the materials available; says she wanted to do something for her during "these war times"; says her father is not home yet; gives list of things Rebecca needs.
      - "Mother" [Selina L. Powell], n.p., to one of daughters [Rebecca, Hattie, or Nina], n.p., [1861-1865]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Discusses the importance of having nice handwriting; describes Kate's [?] studies; grieves over how many have lost their homes and hopes that her daughter could have a couple years holiday (from teaching); says those who must have employment are happiest; writes of family and friends; discusses her Uncle G's [?] method of teaching.
        Incomplete (first part missing). Including attached insert saying that Mr. H. [?] declined her father's services.
      - "Cousin" S[arah] J. (Powell) C[onrad], n.p., to [Re]Bec[ca] [Powell], n.p., [1861-1863]., 4 pages. ALS. Incomplete, first part missing. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Describes the scene when the Yankees came into the home of Dr. Robert Baldwin; says Dr. Baldwin was kicked out of town because he refused to pay a servant; describes how the town has changed since the Yankees have taken over; mentions a man named Milroy who seems to be their leader; gives news of family members many of whom has been sick; describes a puppy he has gotten; describes a battle in which many Yankees were taken as prisoners; says Milroy has escaped and has gone to Washington; says all of her furniture is not sold and that they cannot try to sell it while the Yankees are here; discusses Dr. Daniel Conrad's practice.
      - "Sister" S[elina] Powell, n.p. to Mary (Mrs. Frank Lloyd), Charlotte C[our]t House,[Charlotte County, Virginia], n.d. [1861-1865]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Asks what Jeanie [?] will do all summer; says she has heard that all the carriage horses in Gloucester have been carried off; says she will go to Powhatan to join her husband who is working for Mr. Michaux; says the Yankees are in Shepherdstown but that the Confederates have Winchester.
      - [Mary Custis Lee], Lexington, [Virginia], to Selina [(Lloyd) Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 10 January [post 1865]., 2 pages. AL. Xcy included. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Speaks of the last four years, the excitement and the trials; discusses "the college" that Robert is involving with; discusses the difficulty of finding good help; describes their house, saying it is handsome to "confederate eyes"; expresses sadness that her home is still used by the Yankees; discusses Alexandria.
      - S[elina] Powell, Prince Edward [County],[Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 15 June [1861-1865]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Comments on the postal problems and hopes she has been receiving her letters; gives news of the Bookers; writes of her anxiety over how she [Nina] is and discusses her travel plans to Prince Edward; discusses where the Yankees are stationed; writes of the family's plans for the summer.
      - S[elina] P[owell], n.p., to Nina [Powell],[Richmond, Virginia], [1861-1865]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Sends her cotton for stockings; comments on postal problems; discusses the safety of Richmond; discusses sewing and fashions; news of family and friends.
      - [Selina Powell], n.p., to [?], n.p., [1861-1865]., 2 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Discusses the dilemma of Southerns taking the "oath" with the Northerners so that they can protect their property.
      - "Mother" S[elina] Powell, n.p., to [Nina Powell], n.p., [1861-1865]., 2 pages. ALS. Incomplete, first part missing. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Reports that Captain Watkins and Willie Dupuy have been wounded; says she does not know which battle they were in; news of friends; says she has heard from Mr. Powell recently; discusses dresses.
      - R[ebecca] P[owell], n.p., to Nina [Powell], n.p., [1861-1865]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Says that she sent socks to Willie [?] who is in the army; mentions the death of James M[coughty?].
      - [Selina Powell], n.p., to [one of her daughters], n.p., [1861-1865?]., 2 pages. AL. Incomplete. (Box-folder 4:7)
        Describes how to make Mrs. Sharpe's [?] hat; describes Lute's hat; says she will get two or three hundred dollars in Northern money from an Uncle William.
    - Papers, 1866., 34 items. (Box-folder 5:1)
      - Rebecca C. Powell, Greenwood Depot, [?], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 10 January [18]66., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Discusses teaching; describes trip to Charlottesville and adventurous train ride; mentions Sandy Pendleton's [?] wedding; discusses Trip's [?] health.
      - M[ary] C[ustis] Lee, Lexington, [Virginia], to [Rebecca C. Powell], [Alexandria, Virginia], 20 January [1866]., 2 pages. ALS. Including Xcy. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Sends Rebecca a picture of Robert E. Lee, taken during the war (picture is dated 20 January 1866); writes of Lexington where they have just moved; gives news of family.
      - Rebecca [Powell], Liberty Hall, [Willow Bank, Virginia?], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 27 January [18]66., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Describes her social activities; gives teaching position that Hattie is considering; reports that Yankees are being strict in their town.
      - C[harles] L[loyd] Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to "daughter" [either Rebecca, Nina, or Hattie Powell], n.p., 28 January 1866., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Discusses poor mail service; describes Alexandria as dull town with spirit of despondency, town may be forced into the District of Columbia; describes visit of Henry Hallowell [?]; much family and town news.
      - Becca [Rebecca Powell], Greenwood Depot, [?], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 28 January., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Discusses crocheting, books they have read; much family news and gossip.
      - "Cousin" Emily [Forrest?], Baltimore, to Nina [Powell], n.p., 2 February 1866., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Discusses family news; speaks of financial situation of buying a house in Baltimore; discusses problems of retrieving household items (portraits, furniture, etc.) and where to put them.
      - "Cousin" E[mily] D. [Forrest?], Baltimore, to Nina [Powell], n.p., 7 February 1866., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Discusses details of retrieving family possessions from the Office of Confiscation; includes list of objects missing.
      - Hattie L. Powell, Richmond, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell], Alexandria, Virginia, 8 February 1866., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Describes her trip and her stay with Cousin Lee; tells of relatives and other people she has seen; will continue traveling.
      - Hattie L. Powell, n.p., to Nina [Powell],"Rolling View", [?], 18 February 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Discusses daily life and schedule; family news.
      - Hattie L. Powell, "Rolling View", [?], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 6 March [1866]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Describes her trip to Dr. Wights' and tells of the people she met there; discusses dresses; asks about the family.
      - C[harles] L. Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to "daughters" [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 11 March 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Description of the political happenings in Washington D.C.: the disputes between President Johnson and the "Radicals", Mr. Johnson's veto message, the South's need to have representation in Congress; tells his view of these happenings; discusses attempts to retrieve articles from the confiscation office; family news.
      - "Friend" Mary G. Palcoke, Solitaire, [Richmond, Virginia?], to Nina [Powell], Duke Street, Alexandria, [Virginia], 12 March [18]66., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Tells of difficulty she has dealing with hard life of times, "Yankee" rule, and free Negroes; much news about friends in the neighborhood.
      - Rebecca C. Powell, "Liberty Hall", [Nelson County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 14 March [18]66., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Describes dinner at New Market and the people she saw there; describes conditions of roads, outlawing carriage rides; much news of family and friends.
      - "Sister" H[attie] L. Powell,"Rolling View", [?] to [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 18 March [18]66., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Tells of people she has seen or heard from.
      - S[elina] Powell, Alexandria, [Virginia], to "daughter" [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 18 March 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Discusses family news and news of friends; talks of sewing projects.
      - Hattie [Powell],"Rolling View", [?], Nina [Powell], n.p., 4 April [1866]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Gives an account of her "Easter excursion," reporting what she did and whom she met; says Mrs. Atkins has no servants, so she will have to clean her own room.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Linden", [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 24 April 1866., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Describes events of neighborhood; tells news of friends; tells of religious happenings, Mr. Wharey's [?] reform in the church, and her religious sentiments; writes of her gloomy feelings about the South, her distrust of the Yankees, and her rebellious feels toward them; congratulates Nina on having her own "home."
      - "Cousin" Emily [Forrest?], Cumberland, [Maryland], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 19 May 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Tells of stay in Cumberland with her "sister and brother"; tells of problems in retrieving household items lost in war; Douglas' [Forrest?][her husband?] law practice is improving.
      - "Sister" Hattie L. Powell, "Rolling View", [?], to Nina [Powell], Corner of Washington and Duke St[reet]s, Alexandria, Virginia, 21 May 1866., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Asks Nina to welcome her friend, Mr. Henry T[heodore] Wight, who brings the letter, and make his stay in Alexandria pleasant.
      - Hattie [Powell],"Rolling View", [?], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 28 May 1866., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Tries to convince Nina to take a trip next summer; describes new bonnet styles; describes her friend [Henry] Theodore Wight who will be taking a trip to Alexandria; discusses clothes.
      - Hattie [Powell],"Rolling View", [?], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 1 June [1866]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Gives her view on the family taking in boarders, saying children would be easier for their mother to handle; asks about the "Council"; reports on what she has done socially; discusses the dresses she has made; says that yesterday the people of Richmond decorated the Confederate soldiers' graves; says she wishes she had gone; says Mrs. Adkins did not go, but sent flowers to Richmond.
        Written on ALS from J. Walker, Dover [?], to Hattie [Powell], Rolling Views, n.d. Sends her flowers and asks her to come to visit him. 1 page.
      - Hattie [Powell],"Rolling View", [?], to "sister" [Rebecca Powell], n.p., 12 June 1866., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Describes her visit to Richmond, people she visited, and how many commented on how well she looked compared to last winter; describes clothes she is making.
      - R[ebecca] C. P[owell],"Liberty Hall", Nelson County, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 15 June [1866]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Asks her to send ribbon for a dress she will wear to a day-long affair at Norwood; news of friends.
      - Hattie L. Powell, "Rolling View", [?], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 18 June [1866]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Discusses their plans to go to Prince Edward County; discusses what clothes she has and what she may need; news of family and friends.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Linden", [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 11 July 1866., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Explains why she cannot attend the gathering at Mr. Redd's that night; says she must listen to her head and not her heart so that she may get well; says she is tired of feeling ill and weak.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Linden", [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell], Falkland, [?], 16 August 1866., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Invites Nina and Hattie Powell to come stay with them; says she feels better and is very excited to see them.
      - Lettie [Lavelette][?], "Linden", [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 22 September 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Expresses her joy that she arrived home safely, and her regret that her mother [Selina Powell] has taken ill; describes a [jousting] tournament among young boys or "knights," in which the girls were honored as Queens and Maids of Honor; news about family and friends.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Linden", [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina L. Powell, Alexandria, Virginia, 10 October 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Gives her condolences for her uncle's death and her mother's illness; tells her of Nancy's [Lettie's sister] engagement and tells Nina not to leave her to marry a man; much news of family and friends.
      - "Friend" Nannie [Nancy] [?] [Lavalette's sister], Linden, [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 3 November 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Thanks Nina for her letter congratulating her and Willie Booker on their engagement; news about her fiance; tells her adventures of keeping the house while her mother was gone; news of family and friends.
      - "Mother" [Selina Powell], Charlotte, [?], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 7 November 1866[?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Writes that her father is looking for board for her [Selina] and until then she will stay in Charlotte; recommends that Nina not write to men unless she is engaged to him or unless he is an old family friend; news of family and friends.
      - Rebecca C. Powell, Greenwood Depot, [?], to "Mother" [Selina L. Powell], n.p., 22 November [1866?]., 4 pages. AL. Incomplete, last portion of letter missing. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Discusses how far they are apart but thinks it is best that she (her mother) stay at Uncle Fred's; says she will stay at school for Christmas; writes of family and friends; tells that her health is very good and that she weights 106 pounds; discusses her school duties and her sewing.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Linden" [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell], n.p., 28 November 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Describes the parties she has had at her home recently; speaks of the engagement between Willie Booker and Nancy [her sister], and Lou Edmunds and Captain Hill; news of family and friends.
      - "Friend" Nannie [Nancy] [?], "Linden" [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 12 December 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Tells how she and her friends have been together for three weeks now, staying at different homes; wishes Nina could be there; news of courting, engagements and weddings; tells Nina that she will not become an old maid; much news about family and friends; discusses Reading Societies and books read.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Linden", [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina L. Powell, Alexandria, Virginia, 18 December 1866., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:1)
        Tells of courtings, engagements and weddings; tells of Christmas plans; discusses the struggle in the Christian life to be pure.
    - Papers, 1867., 15 items. (Box-folder 5:2)
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Linden", [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Nina Powell, Alexandria, Virginia, 10 January 1867., 8 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Describes Christmas holidays; discusses the Christian struggle for purity; says she is having more headaches; discusses poor financial situation with no patrons paying for her teachings.
      - Nannie [Nancy], "Falkland", [Prince Edward County], [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 1 February 1867., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Describes the changes taking place: their Uncle Joe has died and she, Lavalette and her mother have moved to Falkland to take care of his children; she and Lavalette will teach the children; Lavalette is feeling worse; her brother and sister May will take care of Linden; news of engagements, weddings, family and friends.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Falkland", Prince Edward County, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 16 February 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Describes her new home and her new schedule; news about family and friends.
      - Nannie [Nancy] [?], "Falkland", [Prince Edward County], [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 21 March 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Tells about her fiance's [Willie Booker] work in [Medical School]; describes reactions to the Territorial Bill and to Gen[eral] Scofield[s]; wonders if Lavalette will keep her promise to become an old maid; says the weather is so bad that they will not be able to go to Church for a month because of the roads; says she is trying to guess when weddings will be by who is making their wedding clothes.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Falkland", [Prince Edward County], [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 22 March 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Describes her teaching job with her sister Nancy; describes her students; tells how spirits have been low since the passage of the Territorial Bill, says their district is commanded by Gen[eral] Schofield; describes the "demoralizing" incident of one of the county men running off with a Negro girl and marrying her; news of family and friends.
      - M. C. Lee, Lexington, Virginia, to Rebecca [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 18 April 1867., 2 pages. ALS. Xcy included. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Sends this letter through a friend and asks Rebecca to mail a package to Washington, D.C. for her; may have some frames sent to her, which could then be sent to them by steamboat to Richmond and canal boat to Lexington; says Mildred is in Richmond; Rob and Fitzhugh may go to Jennie's[?] wedding.
      - Nannie [Nancy] [?], "Falkland", [Prince Edward County], [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 14 June 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Describes the commencement exercises that she and Lavalette attended at Hampden Sydney; describes the fashions she saw there; says the scrub worm is seriously damaging the tobacco crop; describes their summer bonnets bought in Richmond.
      - Lettie [Lavalette] [?], "Falkland", [Prince Edward County], [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 8 July 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Says that Nancy [her sister] has been ill; says that she, Nancy and their mother will take a trip North for their health; says she dreads to be among the Yankees; tells that Lou Booker has typhoid fever and so her wedding must be postponed; discusses the advantages and disadvantages of being an old maid and whether they will be one.
      - Hattie [Powell], Alexandria, Virginia, to Nina [Powell],[Berryville], [?], 21 August 1867., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Gives news of gentlemen who are courting her; says that John Smith has been visiting her every other night; tells Nina that it is becoming serious and that she better come home soon or she will be gone; gives advice on the gentlemen that Nina is seeing.
      - Nannie [Nancy] [?], Danville, [Virginia], to Nina [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 11 October 1867., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Describes their stay in Danville; tells that her engagement with Willie Booker has been terminated; discusses their plans of where to live next year; news of family and friends; discusses fair.
      - "Grandmother" Catharine Powell, Leesburg, [Virginia], to Hattie [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 22 October 1867., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Thanks Hattie for her announcement of her "change of condition" [marriage or engagement?]; gives her best wishes for her health and happiness.
      - [Mrs. Robert E. Lee], Lexington, [Virginia], to Rebecca [Powell],[Alexandria, Virginia], 28 October [1867?]., 4 pages. AL. Including Xcy. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Discusses which furniture and portraits she would like to be sent to her.
      - M. C. Lee, Lexington, [Virginia], to Rebecca [Powell], Alexandria, Virginia, 16 November 1867?., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Discusses details of sending furniture from Alexandria to Lexington and of having portraits framed and sent.
        Includes notes to Selina and Nina. Including Xcy.
      - M[ary] C[ustis] Lee, Lexington, [Virginia], to Rebecca [C. Powell], n.p., 24 December [1867?]., 2 pages. ALS. Xcy included. (Box-folder 5:2)
        Discusses her transactions to acquire more furnishings for their home; news about family and friends.
      - Hattie [Powell], n.p., to [Nina Powell?], n.p., [1862-1867?]., 2 pages. ALS. Incomplete, first part missing. (Box-folder 5:2)